Guide to the Incunabula Collection at Stanford University, 1467-1500
Department of Special Collections
- Proba, 4th cent. Virgiliocentones Veteris et Noui Testamenti.[Leipzig: Printer of Capotius (Martin Landsberg?), ca. 1490], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1490 .P76; [40] p. (last p. blank); 19 cm.
  References: Goff (rev.), P-985. ISTC (RLIN), ip00985000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: untouched. Binding: full leather, marbled endpapers. Spine title: Proba. Provenance: R. Hildebrand, 1851 (inscription); ink-stamp of three-petaled flower within a shield.
- Petrarca, Francesco, 1304-1374. Franciscus Petrarcha De remedijs vtriusq[ue] fortune.[Heidelberg: Heinrich Knoblochtzer?, ca. 1490], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1490 .P384; [4], CXII, CXXX leaves; 21 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., III, p. 672 (IA.12984). Goff (rev.), P-408. Hain-Copinger 12791. ISTC (RLIN), ip00408000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: Capitals and paragraph marks in blue and red; initial strokes in red. Binding: full brown morocco. Binder's title: Petrarch. Edge title: Franc. Petrarcij De remedijs vtriusq[ue] fortunae. Provenance: Ewald Flgel Library (booklabel).
- Regio, Rafaello, d. 1520. Raphaelis Regii epistolae Plynii: qua libri Naturalis historiae Tito Vespasiano dedicantur enarrationes; euisdem de q[ua]tuor Persii locis: uno Valerii Maximi duobus Tullii De officiis ac tribus oratoriis q[ues]stio[n]ibus disputatio; euisdem de quibusdam Quintliani locis cum quodam Calfurnio dialogus; eiusdem loci cuiusdam Quintiliani ac eius Cicerouis [sic] ad Atticum epistolae cuius initium est Epistolam hanc co[n]uicio efflagitarunt codicilli tui enarratio.[Venice]: Gulielmus Tridinensis cognomento Anima Mia cuius opera hoc opusculum Venetiis fuit descriptum Principe Augustino Barbadico, decimo calendas Iunias Mcccclxxxx [23 May 1490], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1490 .R38; [76] p. (last 2 blank); 21 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., V, p. 411 (IA.23077). Goff (rev.), R-116. Hain-Copinger 13810. ISTC (RLIN), ir00116000.
  Stanford copy: Errata on p. [74]. Stanford copy 1 (RBC): one initial in black. Binding: decorated wrappers; in case with title: Epistolae Plynii. Provenance: William Salloch (bookseller's label).
- Regiomontanus, Joannes, 1436-1476. Tabule directionu[m] profectionu[m]q[ue] famosissimi viri Magistri Ioannis Germani de Regiomonte in natiuitatibus multum vtiles. [Tabella sinus recti, per gradus [et] singula minuta divisa: ad tabulas directionu[m] M[a]g[ist]ri Iohannis de Regiomonte necessarias cum quibus exemplis].[Augsburg]: Erhardiq[ue] Ratdolt mira imprimendi arte, qua nuper Venetijs nunc Auguste Vindelicorum excellit nominatissimus, 4 nonas Ianuarij [2 Jan.] 1490., Call No. Barchas Collection KA1490 .R44; [312] p.; 20 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., II, p. 383 (IA.6698). Goff (rev.) R-112. Hain 13801*. ISTC, ir00112000. Klebs 834.1.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (BARCH): Imperfect: p. [61]-[278] (e-r* s*) only. Titles and signatures from BM 15th cent. Binding: blue wrappers.
- Rolevinck, Werner, 1425-1502. Fasciculus te[m]po[rum] omnes antiquorum cronicas complecte[n]s. Title: Fasciculus temporum omnes antiquorum cronicas complectens.[Strasbourg: Jean Prss, not before 1490], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1490 .R65; [6], XC, [2] (blank) leaves: ill. (woodcuts); 27 cm.
  References: Goff (rev.), R-276. Hain-Copinger 6916. ISTC, ir00276000. Polain 3362.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: captials and initial strokes added in red on some leaves of Tabula Prohemium. Ms. marginalia (some trimmed) and underscoring. Imperfect: lacks 2 final blanks. Binding: vellum sheet from an early missal; fold-over fore-edges; one tab. Shelf-label on spine: 182.
- Sacro Bosco, Joannes de, fl. 1230. Sphaera mundi. Hoc ... opusculum impressum est Venetiis: Mandato expensis ... Octauiani Scoti, ciuis Modoetiensis, 1490 quarto Nonas Octobris [4 Oct.], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1490 .S2; [96] p.: ill. (woodcut), diagrams (woodcuts, some col.); 23 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., V, p. 438 (IA.22845). Goff (rev.) J-409. Hain-Copinger 14113. ISTC, ij00409000. Stillwell J.368. Polain 2303. Proctor 5023.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Binding: limp vellum. Provenance: Charles Albert Browne (bookplate); [A. Jios?] Hi[er?] Alb[?] Brisi[cs?]oll. D. mi[?] (inscription); extensive ms. marginalia underscoring.
- Ambrose, Saint, Bishop of Milan, d. 397. Tabula Epistola[rum] ... I[m]pressa su[n]t i[n] i[n]clyta ciuitate Mediolani: Per Antoniu[m] Zarotu[m] Parme[n]sem, anno Domini 1491, in Cale[n]dis Februarii [1 Feb.], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1491 .A43 F; [384] p.; 32 cm.
  References: BM 15th century, VI, p. 722 (IB.26062). BN cat. des incun., A-292. GW 1601. Goff (rev.), A-553. Hain-Copinger 899. ISTC (RLIN), ia00553000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Untouched. Imperfect: 1st 2 leaves (table and dedicatory letter) lacking. Binding: quarter blind-stamped leather; boards; leather metal clasps. Title on lower cover: S. Ambro. Epis.; edge title: S. Ambrosii Episto. Provenance: Giorgio di Veroli (booklabel); ms. marginalia and underscoring.
- Benzi, Ugo, 1376-1439. Excellentissimi viri Vgonis senensis in prima[m] fen primi canonis Auicene expositio feliciter incipit. Impressum Ferrarie: opera Andree Galli ..., 1491, die v[er]o xiii me[n]sis Augusti [13 Aug.], Call No. Barchas Collection KA1491 .B4 f; [320] p.; 33 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., VI, p. 604 (IB.25711). Goff (rev.), H-544. Hain-Copinger-Reichling, 9016. ISTC, ih00544000. Klebs, 998.1. Stillwell, M.B. Science, 303.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (BARCH): Rubrication: paragraph marks and initial- strokes added in red or brown. Binding: modern vellum, in red half- morocco case. Binder: James MacDonald Co., New York City (stamp on case). Spine title: Hugo Senensis expositio. Ferrara. Case title: Expositio Avicene. Provenance: Robert Honeyman IV (bookplate); ms. marginalia underscoring.
- Brack, Wenceslaus, 15th cent. Vocabularius rerum.[Leipzig]: Impressum Liptzck per Conradum Kachelouenn, anno D[ominu]m m cccc lxxxxi tercia feria post Assumptionis Mariae Virginis Gloriose ... [16 Aug. 1491], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1491 .B7; XXXXX leaves; 21 cm.
  References: Goff (rev.), B-1066. GW 4992. Hain-Reichling, 3706. ISTC (RLIN), ib01066000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: Initial large capital, initials, initial strokes, and paragraph marks in red. Binding: full vellum; ms. title on spine: Brack. 1491; in case. Provenance: E. Meyer 1839 (inscription); The Hildebrand Library (ink-stamp); ms. underscoring; ms. marginalia.
- Bible. O.T. Apocrypha. Maccabees, 2nd, I. Latin. Vulgate. 1491. [Two leaves from the 1491 Vulgate Bible] Bible. N.T. Acts, XVIII-XIX. Latin. Vulgate. 1491.[Basel: Johann Froben, 27 June 1491], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1491 .B52; [4] p.; 23 cm.
  References: BMC XVth cent., III, p. 789 (IA.37873). Darlow Moule, 6086. Goff (rev.), B-592. GW 4269. Hain-Copinger 3107. ISTC (RLIN), ib00592999.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: Initials in red. Binding: red paste-grain, decorative endpapers; leaves mounted, showing recto only of each leaf. Binder's title: Two pages from the first hand Bible Basel 1491. Front free endpaper mutilated.
- Boethius, d. 524. Boetij viri celeberrimi De consolat[i]one philosophie liber: cum optimo co[m]mento Beati Thome. Inclyte Arge[n]tine[n]siu[m] vrbis i[n]dustria fabrefact[us]: [Johann Prss, before 6 Mar. 1491], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1491 .B64; [380] p. (last p. blank); 21 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., III, p. 860 (IA.2540). Copinger 1102. Goff (rev.), B-792. GW 4550. Hain 3367. ISTC (RLIN), ib00792000. Pellechet 2497.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Untouched. Imperfect: t.p. repaired. Binding: quarter leather; boards; clasps lacking. Edge title: Boetii opera. Provenance: Ewald Flgel (booklabel and ink-stamp); ms. marginalia and underscoring. With: Pseudo-Boethius. Boetius De disciplina scholarium. Colonia: In alma Vniuersitate Colon[ensis] impressus in domo Henrici Que[n]tell iuxta summu[m], anno Virginalis partus 1498 mensis Martij die quinta.
- Pseudo-Boethius. Boetius De disciplina scholarium: cum notabili co[m]mento. Colonia: In alma Vniuersitate Colon[ensis] impressus in domo Henrici Que[n]tell iuxta summu[m], anno Virginalis partus 1498 mensis Martij die quinta., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1491 .B64; [132] p. (last p. blank); 21 cm.
  References: Goff (rev.), B-827. GW 4603. Hain-Copinger, 3425. ISTC (RLIN), ib00827000. Pellechet 2564.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy1 (RBC): Untouched. Imperfect: last leaf detached and pasted to the lower end paper. With: Boethius. Boetij viri celeberrimi De consolat[i]one philosophie liber. Inclyte Arge[n]tine[n]siu[m] vrbis i[n]dustria fabrefact[us]: [Johann Prss, before 6 Mar. 1491].
- Dante Alighieri, 1265-1321. Comento di Christophoro Landino fiorentino sopra La comedia di Danthe Alighieri poeta fiorentino. Impressi i[n] Venesia: P[er] Bernardino Benali Matthio da Parma ..., del. MCCCCLXXXXI. adi iii. Marzo [3 Mar. 1491], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1491 .D36 f; [10], CCLXXXXI, [1] leaves: ill. (woodcuts); 31 cm.
  Includes (leaves L7v-L8r) the suppositious Credo, Pater Noster and Ave Maria.
  References: BM 15th cent., V, p. 373 (IB.22339) Goff (rev.), D-32. GW 7969. Hain 5949. ISTC (RLIN), id00032000 Pellechet 4117.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): A variant of BM 15th cent., V, p. 373,with the additional words in the colophon as cited in Pellechet. Rubrication: woodcut initials and illustrations colored blue and red, green and yellow; coat of arms on lower edge of full page woodcut facing leaf a2; leaf a2 has floral border in gilt and color, and coat of arms at foot of text; small capitals supplied in blue and red. Binding: brown leather, stamped in gilt and blind, with medallion of Dante set into covers; gilt paneled spine; marbled endpapers; in slipcase. Binder's title: Dante col commento di C. Landino. Provenance: Giorgio Fanan (bookplate); ms. marginalia.
- Landino, Cristoforo, 1424-1504. Comento di Christophoro Landino fiorentino sopra la comedia di Danthe Alighieri poeta fiorentino: proemio.[Venice: Bernardinus Benalius and Matteo Capcasa, 3 Mar. 1491], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1491 .D362 f; [20] p.; 31 cm. NOTES: The first ten leaves of the March 3, 1491 Divina commedia,comprising the Proemio by Christoforo Landino. Cf. BM 15th cent., V, p. 373 (IB.22339); Goff (rev.), D-32; GW 7969; Hain 5949; ISTC (RLIN), id00032000. Title from caption, in which "Proemio" precedes "Comento."
  References: Imprint from Goff (rev.), D-32. Woodcut capitals.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Underscoring; ms. marginalia.
- Dante Alighieri, 1265-1321. Comento di Christophoro Landino fiorentino sopra La comedia di Danthe Alighieri poeta fiorentino. Impresso in Vinegia: Per Petro Cremonese dito Veronese, adi xviii. di Noue[m]brio M.cccc.Lxxxxi [18 Nov. 1491], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1491 .D363 f; [14], 11-316 [i.e. 317], [3] leaves: ill. (woodcuts); 31 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., V, p. 270 (IB.20863). Goff (rev.), D-33. GW 7970. Hain-Copinger-Reichling 5950. ISTC (RLIN), id00033000. "Cancione dello excellentissimo poeta Dante Aldigeri": r2v-r6v.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Addendum: full page woodcut from the March 3, 1491 ed. bound in facing B1, hand colored, with coats of arms at lower edge. Rubrication: blue and red initials; colored illustrations. Imperfect: lacks a** (first sequence), g8, k4.5, l1, and all after leaf p7. Numerous errors in foliation. Binding: half calf, brown boards, title label on spine; marbled endpapers. Binder's title: Dante Divina commedia. Provenance: Alessandro Lisca questo libro e del [1588?] (inscription); Giorgio Fanan (bookplate); extensive ms. marginalia, trimmed. Stanford copy 2 (RBC): Imperfect: lacks a** (1st sequence) and r6. Leaves p1-q8 misbound preceding leaf o1. Errors in foliation. Leaves 2A*, r1, and r3-r5 repaired. Binding: full pigskin; in slipcase. Binder's title: Dante 1491. Underscoring and ms. marginalia.
- Livy. M. An. Sabellicus magnifico et praestanti viro Benedicto Cornario patritio Veneto salutem. Impressum Venetiis: [Johannes Rubeus Vercellensis], 1491 die v nouembris ..., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1491 .L58 f; [23], 2-91, 84-ccxxxii leaves (1st p. and last p. blank); 33 cm.
  Includes (leaves [9]-[23] (1st sequence)): L. Flori Epitoma decadum quattuordecim T. Livii Patavini Historici in centum et quadraginta libros distinctum.
  References: BN cat. des incun, L-184. BSB-Ink L-193. Goff (rev.), L-245. Hain 10137. ISTC (RLIN), il00245000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Untouched. Imperfect: leaves [6]-[7] (1st sequence; both blank) lacking. Binding: full leather; panelled spine; title label on spine; repair work on either side of spine. Binder's title: Livii Historia.
- Alfonso X, King of Castile and Leon, 1221-1284. Tabule astronomice Alfonsi Regis. Venetijs: Opera [et] arte mirifica viri solertis Ioha[n]nis Hamman de Landoia dictus Hertzog ..., 1492 currente: pridie Calen[das] Nouembr[is] [31 Oct.], Call No. Barchas Collection KA1492 .A4; [228] p. (last p. blank); 22 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., V, p. 424 (IA.23354). Goff (rev.) A-535. GW 1258. Hain 869*. ISTC, ia00535000. Klebs 50.2. Rhodes 66.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (BARCH): Binding: wooden boards, remains of tooled leather spine; remains of clasp on upper fore-edge; guards of vellum ms. fragments on 1st and last gatherings. Extensive ms. marginalia.
- Alanus, de Insulis, d. 1202. Alanus De maximis theologie.[Basel: Jacob von Pfortzheim, ca. 1492], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1492 .A33; [80] p. (last blank); 21 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., III, p. 776 (IA.37701). BN cat. des incun., A-93. Goff (rev.), A-181. GW 510. Hain-Copinger 389*. ISTC (RLIN), ia00181000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: initial, initial strokes, paragraph marks, and underscoring in red. Binding: quarter blind- stamped calf, panelled spine, oaken boards, remnants of clasp. Provenance: Collegij Soctis Jesu Bruntruti (inscription); Edw. Barnhome (signature); William Salloch (bookseller's label).
- Bruni, Leonardo, 1369-1444. Le historie eiorentine [i.e., fiorentine]. Impresso in Firenze: Per Bartholomeo p. fiorentino, nellanno del 1492, adi V di giugno., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1492 .B78 f; [444] p.; 34 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., VI, p. 649 (IB.27292). Goff (rev.), B-1248. GW 5613 (I). Indexed by: Hain-Copinger 1563. Hain-Copinger 13173. ISTC (RLIN), ib01248000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: large initial and floral border, including shield, in gold, blue, red and green on leaf a2r; other initials in blue. Imperfect: typographical error on t.p. corrected. Binding: blind-stamped leather over boards; rebacked; remnants of clasps. Binder's title: Le historie fiorentine. Binding variant: table ([rum]1-[rum]4) bound before t.p. and followed by 1 blank leaf not found in other described copies. Provenance: Jacobi P.R. Lyell (bookplate) and .... Denkmalamt (ink-stamp); ms. foliation in Roman and Arabic nos.; ms. marginalia.
- Jacobus Philippus, Bergomensis, 1434-1520. Supplementum chronicharum. Impressum autem Venetijs: Per magistrum Bernardinum Ricium de Nouaria, anno a Natiuitate D[omi]ni M.cccc.lxxxxij. die decimoquinto Februarij ... [15 Feb. 1492 i.e. 1493], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1492 .J25 f; [2], 256, [12] leaves: ill. (woodcuts); 32 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., V, p. 404 (IB.22654). Goff (rev.), J-212. Hain-Copinger 2809. ISTC (RLIN), ij00212000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: untouched. Binding: half vellum, marbled paper boards. Binder's title: Jacobi Bergom Chronicorum Supplementum 1492. Provenance: Philipps (inscription); ms. marginalia; fists.
- Virgil. Publii Virgilii Maronis Opera: cum Seruii Mauri Honorati grammatici, Aelii Donati, Christophori Landini, atq[ue] Short title: Domitii Calderini co[m]mentariis. Nurnberge: Imp[re]ssa impe[n]sis Anthonii Koberger, Anno [Christ]i M.ccccxcii [1492], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1492 .V6 F; [8], CCCXLV, [1] leaves; 30 cm.
  References: BMC 15th cent. II:436 (IB. 7441). Copinger 6070. Goff V-188. ISTC (RLIN HPB), UKBYIV00188000-E. Oates 1024. Polain 3963. Proctor 2081 (types 22, 23 and Greek).
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Imperfect: leaves CCXXXII, CCXXXVII first last blank leaves lacking. Binding: "execute pour la Lib. Louis Conard;" half red morocco, marbled boards. Provenance: James V. Brown Library, Williamsport, Pa. (booklabel); extra leaf of ms. index bound at front; extensive underscoring and marginalia in red black, especially at beginning; extensive ms. notes on leaf [1]v; ms. music on leaf LXXVIIIv.
- Chalcondyles, Demetrius, ca. 1424-1510 or 1511. Erotemata Title: Demetriou Chalkondylou Erotemata synoptika ton okto tou logou meron meta tinon chresimon kanonon.[Milan: Uldericus Scinzenzeler, ca. 1493], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1493 .C43; 396 p.; 27 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., VI, p. 767 (IB.26861). Goff (rev.), D-139. GW 8250. Hain-Copinger-Reichling, 6093. Pellechet 4189. ISTC (RLIN), ic00419860.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Untouched. Imperfect: lacks 3rd work (leaves 129-148). Binding: red morocco, gilt decorated with gilt arms stamped on upper and lower covers; gilt decorated panelled spine with title label; gilt turn-ins; marbled endpapers; all edges gilt. Binder's title: Erotemat. Provenance: Chatsworth (booklabel); ms. marginalia.
- Dante Alighieri, 1265-1321. Danthe Alegieri Fiorentino. Impressa in Venetia: Per Matheo di Chodecha da Parma, del 1493 adi XXIX de nouembre [29 Nov. 1493], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1493 .D36 f; [10], II-CCXCIX [i.e. CCC], [1] leaves: ill.; 33 cm.
  References: BM 15th Cent., V, p. 484 (IB.22753). GW 7971. Goff (rev.), D-34. Hain-Reichling, 5952. Hain 5951. ISTC (RLIN), id00034000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Binding: quarter blind-stamped leather; wooden boards; clasps lacking. Provenance: Giorgio Fanan (bookplate); mss. marginalia.
- Giles, of Rome, Archbishop of Bourges, ca. 1243-1316. Domini Egidij de Roma archiepiscopi Bituricensis ac primatis aq[ua]tanie diui ordinis fratrum heremitarum Sancti Augustini philozophorum ac theologorum fundatissimi Theoreumatum de esse et essencia tractatus.[Leipzig]: Industria et arte Conradi Kacheloffen, anno incarnati verbi 1493., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1493 .G55; [72] p.; 20 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., III, p. 626 (IA.11551) Goff (rev.), A-80. GW 7211. Hain 120*. ISTC (RLIN), ia00080000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: initials and initial strokes in red. Binding: modern vellum. Extensive ms. marginalia (some loss due to trimming) and underscoring.
- Maneken, Carolus. Formule epistolaru[m] Domini Karoli.[Strasbourg: Georg Husner], 1493., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1493 .M36; [6], XCV, [1] (blank) leaves; 21 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., I, p. 160 (IA.2332). ISTC, im00185000. Goff (rev.), M-185. Hain-Copinger, 10679.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): p8 used as lower paste-down. Binding: half pigskin, wooden boards, remains of clasp; paper label on upper cover in ms.: Grammatica nova. Binding error: leaves d1.8 and d2.7 bound preceding c3. Ms. vellum guard, gathering p. Provenance: Casparus Boetius [Alonaceri?] (inscription); Conventus Monocansis Carmelitar[um] (inscription); The Brother Julian F.S.C. Collection, Manhattan College, New York (bookplate); extensive ms. marginalia and underlining.
- Ovid, 43 B.C.-17 or 18 A.D. P. Ouidii Nasonis Metamorphoseos libri: cum commento. Venetiis impressum: Per Bonetum Locatellu[m]: Mandato expe[n]sis nobilis uiri Octauiani Scoti Modoetiensis, anno Salutis 1493, Nonis Iuniis [5 June], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1493 .O95 f; [292] p. (the last 2 p. blank); 30 cm.
  References: Goff (rev.), O-188. Hain-Copinger 12172. ISTC (RLIN), io00188000. Walsh 2298. Colophon in Walsh a variant.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Imperfect: lacks t.p. and last blank leaf. Binding: leather; rebacked with panelled spine and title label; marbled endpapers. Provenance: ms. underscoring and marginalia.
- Schedel, Hartmann, 1440-1514. Liber chronicarum Epitoma operu[m] sex dieru[m] de mu[n]di fabrica., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1493 .S3 f; [Nuremberg]: Hunc librum dominus Anthonius Koberger Nuremberge impressit ... consummatu[m] autem duodecima mensis Iulij anno salutis n[ost]r[a]e 1493 [12 July 1493]
  [20], CCLXVI, [6] (last blank), CCLXVII-CCXCIX, [2] leaves (last blank): ill., coats of arms, maps, ports. (woodcuts); 47 cm.
  References: Known as: Liber Chronicarum, or Nuremberg Chronicle. BM 15th cent. II, p. 437 (IC. 7451). Goff (rev.), S-307. Hain-Copinger 14508. ISTC (RLIN), is00307000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: initial capital on leaf I in gilt, red, blue, and green; other capitals in red and blue, or red. Binding: full red leather, gilt panels on upper and lower cover and spine; armorial crest in gilt on upper cover, with gilt initials SMM above; marbled endpapers. In case, with title: Liber cronicarum. Provenance: Gift of Mrs. Timothy Hopkins (bookplate); Lewis Montolieu (armorial bookplate).
- Schedel, Hartmann, 1440-1514. Register des Buchs der Croniken vnd Geschichten: mit Figure[n] vnd Pildnssen von Anbegi[n]n der Welt bis auf dise v[n]nsere Zeit. Title: Register des Buchs der Croniken und Geschichten[Nuremberg]: Durch ... Anthonien Koberger daselbst zu Nrmberg gedruckt, auf Anregu[n]g vnd Begern ... Sebalden Schreyers vnd Sebastia[n]n Kamermaisters ..., Volbracht a[m]m. xxiij. Tag des Monats Decembris nach der Gepurt Cristi vnssers Haylands M.cccc.xciij. [1493] Iar., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1493 .S315 f; [10], CCLXXXVI, [2] leaves (last leaf blank): ill., coats of arms, maps, ports.; 46 cm.
  Includes (leaves CCLXVIIv-CCLXXXVI) an extract from Aeneas Sylvius' description of Europe.
  References: BM 15th cent., II, p. 437 (IC.7458). Goff (rev.), S-309. Hain 14510. ISTC (RLIN), is00309000. Sabin 77525.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: initials in red and blue, blue, or red; initial strokes (in index) in red. Imperfect: lacks last blank leaf. Binding: blind-stamped leather over boards; clasps; metal decoration on covers lacking; ms. waste used. Provenance: Conventij Bambergensis Ord. B[?]. (inscription); Albert Hooper (booklabel); John M. Stark ... Hull (bookseller's label). Misnumbering of leaves XCIII, CXVI, and CLII corrected.
- Seneca, Lucius Annaeus, ca. 4 B.C.-65 A.D. L. Annei Senecae Tragoediae cu[m] duobus co[m]mentis. Venetiis: Per Matheu[m] Capcasam Parmensem, Mcccclxxxxiii die xviii Iulii [18 July 1493], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1493 .S463 f; [4], CXXXVI [i.e. CXXXXVI] leaves; 32 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., V, p. 484 (IB.22748). Goff (rev.), S-437. Hain-Copinger, 14668. ISTC, is00437000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): untouched. Binding: quarter parchment, brown boards; title label on spine: Seneca. Tragoediae. 1493. In case. Provenance: D. Morgand, Paris (inscription); H.C. Hoskier (signature); William Salloch (bookseller's label).
- Vslegunge der Hymbs nach der Zitt des gantzen Iares.[Strassburg: Johann (Reinhard) Grninger], anno Domini Mcccclxxxxii.ij Kale[n]das deniq[ue] Februarij duodenas [21 Jan. 1494], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1494 .A97; LXXVII [i.e. 79], [1] leaves; 21 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., III, p. 710 (IA.15550). GW 3083. Goff (rev.), A-1397. Hain-Copinger, 2145. ISTC (RLIN), ia01397000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: untouched. Binding: marbled wrappers; in case with title: Auslegung der Hymen. Provenance: The Hildebrand Library (ink-stamp).